Now we are on צדי א' tzadi alef 91 and we start,
thank you so much, we start at the very bottom of צדי
tzadi עמוד ב' amud bet and we are two weeks away from
ending so the
and from beginning the new מסכת masechet but I will tell you
we had a I had a רבי rebbi once in high school
who told me that the פסוק pasuk in קהלת kohelet is like
לב חכם לימינו ולב כסיל לשמאלו lev chacham liyamino velev ksil lismolo
right? So what does that mean? So he says well because the
כסיל ksil the foolish one is looking on his left like oh
how many pages till we finish whereas the חכם chacham is looking
at his right he's saying how many pages have I to חזרה
chazara on right? All
right. So anyway, but it's been a lot of עירובין. eruvin. Anyway
we pick up at the bottom of צדי tzadi עמוד ב' amud
bet and we've been discussing this debate about the חכמים chachamim and
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir about what's considered
you know if you did not make an עירוב eruv which is
the focus of this of this פרק perek what still all one
domain so for a vessel that started within one it can move
to other similar domains again with the assumption that they're all רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid. So אמר רב יהודה amar Rav Yehuda so רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said two lines from the bottom of צדי tzadi
עמוד ב'. amud bet. כשתימצי לומר keshetimtzei lomar על דברי רבי מאיר
al divrei Rebbi Meir when
now that's an interesting phrase כשתימצי לומר keshetimtzei lomar
when you find to say but what it means is like when
you when you like when you really think about it if you
look into it you'll realize that לדיברי רבי מאיר ledivrei Rebbi Meir
גגין רשות לעצמן חצרות רשות לעצמן קרפיפות רשות לעצמן gagin reshut le'atzman
chatzerot reshut le'atzman karpifot reshut le'atzman these three different things rooftops חצרות
chatzerot as we know is the courtyard in front of the houses
and a קרפף karpaf which is basically like a yard it's not
like you know it's it's an enclosed yard and it's not normally
as opposed to the חצר chatzer which is right in front of
the house which is made for the regular use of the house
of the people in the house to bring stuff you know this
is something that's a little bit that's like more distant and not
as regularly used. So these are three different types of domain and
all of them are their own category. So you can carry from
a גג gag to a גג gag or from a חצר chatzer
to a חצר chatzer from a קרפף karpaf to a קרפף karpaf
but you cannot go from one of those to the other. Now
again this is without an עירוב eruv this is vessels that started
in one so you can carry at least vessels that began in
this type of domain within the same type of domain. Okay. I'll
read through it and then I'll say I'll say a word about
how the גמרא Gemara sort of identifies this as the positions in
the משנה. Mishna. So that's רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that each
one of those is a distinct domain. לדיברי רבי שמעון ledivrei Rebbi
Shimon now רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is clearer in the משנה Mishna
as his position because he says you know the language of רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon you might remember was he says that they're all
one domain רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon said in the משנה Mishna אחד
גגות ואחד חצרות ואחד קרפיפות רשות אחת. echad gagot ve'echad chatzerot ve'echad
karpifot reshut achat.
Okay
so they're all one domain. Now the thing is though you could
have read that to mean each one is its own respective רשות.
reshut. Okay and he's and the גמרא Gemara is saying and this'll
be clear it's not so clear in the משנה Mishna but it'll
be clear in a ברייתא braita we're going to quote in a
few minutes that it means they're all the same domain and you
can go from any one of those to any other one of
them. So לדיברי רבי שמעון ledivrei Rebbi Shimon כולן רשות אחת kulan
reshut achat all three combined are one רשות. reshut. All three combined
are one רשות. reshut. Now where do you get that רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir they're distinct? Well we don't yet get it yet but
you'll remember that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir what was the position? Of
let's remind ourselves. Okay what was the three positions?
You had רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon said all one רשות reshut כולן
רשות אחת kulan reshut achat all one רשות. reshut. And what the
גמרא Gemara means now not respective but combined. So גג gag חצר
chatzer and קרפף karpaf are all of the same are all of
the same group. You had רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and the חכמים
chachamim disagreeing right? That רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir about the case of
the two גגות gagot of different people right? Person A and person
B. And רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said that you know all of
the גגות gagot are גגות gagot are one רשות reshut are one
רשות. reshut.
And the חכמים chachamim said since they're owned differently they are different
you know you know different ownership means that they're different. כל אחד
ואחד רשות בפני עצמו. kol echad ve'echad reshut bifnei atzmo. Okay.
So because רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says the גג gag is one
רשות reshut it's sort of reasonable to assume although we're going to
demonstrate it more by evidence that's coming up but it's reasonable to
understand that similarly all חצרות chatzerot are one רשות reshut by themselves
and all קרפיפות karpifot are one רשות reshut by
themselves whereas רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says all of these combined are
one רשות. reshut. And the question therefore is if you did not
make an עירוב eruv and it starts in one can you carry
within that one genre or can you carry from one genre to
the next? How do you define what is one grouping, how do
you define is multiple groupings? Yes.
I mean the idea that all the חצרות chatzerot would be one.
Didn't That was when, yes, if you
mean if you have like a חצר chatzer that didn't make an
עירוב eruv or did, A didn't make an עירוב eruv with B,
you can't go from A to B. That is excellent, that is
for something that started in one of the houses of A. And
then you can't go, so if A, the people of A made
a חצר chatzer you can go from the house of A to
the חצר chatzer of A. But you cannot go from the house
of A to the חצר chatzer of B.
What we're saying is,
if B didn't make an עירוב eruv together with A, but what
we're saying is if even if nobody in A made an עירוב,
eruv, if something started in the חצר chatzer of A, not in
the house of A, in the חצר chatzer of A, you can
go from the חצר chatzer of A to the חצר chatzer of
B. Okay? And that actually your question is going to be relevant
because the גמרא's Gemara about to get to the question of aren't
you afraid it'll get confusing?
So let's actually draw that for a second because you'll laugh because
this whole מסכת... Masechet... Right.
But anyway, okay.
Here you are, here's your חצר chatzer A and here's your חצר
chatzer B. Right, so if you've got,
you have an עירוב, eruv, you have an עירוב, eruv, what can
you do? You can go from the house of A, we'll make
an H-A, to the חצר... chatzer... to that... to the חצר chatzer
of B. Yeah, that's confusing. Okay,
anyway, have to do another way of thinking about this. Anyway, okay.
We'll make little a's for the house.
Okay, so you can go from the house of A into A
with an עירוב. eruv. Without an עירוב eruv you can't. And if
A did not make an עירוב eruv with B, you are not
allowed to go, you cannot go, you can't bring this little a
into there because that started in the house of A. Okay? But
if you had the things that began in the חצר chatzer of
A, right, even if they did not make an עירוב eruv between
the two of them, even if they didn't make an עירוב eruv
amongst themselves, right, if it started in A you can take it
anywhere within A and if it started with A you can bring
it to B if all the חצרות chatzeros are one רשות. reshus.
But not into a house.
But you cannot, yeah, not into a house of B, into the
חצר chatzer of B. Now the גמרא's Gemara question is going to
get to is, one minute, there are you're telling me there could
be two types of objects sitting in this yard if I did
make an עירוב. eruv. One object sitting in this yard started in
A, one object sitting in this yard started in a house and
was brought out if I did make an עירוב eruv it's possible
that it'll be there and I'm supposed to remember which of those
objects I can bring to B and which one I can't? So
the גמרא's Gemara actually going to discuss in a minute that if
I made an עירוב eruv in A, it might not I might
not be allowed to bring anything from A to B because I'll
confuse which thing I'm bringing.
Well what's the point of
making an עירוב eruv then? No, so that I can bring from
the houses of A into the yard of A, right? So anyway,
but we're talking that there's a simple case, no עירוב, eruv, not
only A and B did not make an עירוב, eruv, nobody made
an עירוב eruv at all amongst themselves. Okay, so you cannot bring
anything from the houses out, you're not allowed to bring because there's
no עירוב. eruv. And if somehow something did get brought out, you
can't bring it into the next into the next yard, right? And
but what you still can do is something that starts in A
you can bring to B because all חצרות chatzeros are one domain.
If it starts on a roof or it starts on a קרפף
karpef and according to the חכמים Chachamim even you can even bring
from a roof to a yard to a קרפף. karpef.
And that seems to be according to, I
mean according to רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
And that seems to be according, at least for going from one
חצר chatzer to another, that seems to be according to all opinions.
Right, although we have not explored fully the חכמים Chachamim yet, but
let's but yes, let's assume so. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
תניא כוותיה דרב, tanya k'vasteh d'Rav, תניא כוותיה דרבי יהודה. tanya k'vasteh
d'Rabbi Yehuda. Now we taught like רב, Rav, you might remember רב
Rav from two days ago. רב Rav was the one that said
that according to the חכמים Chachamim that you can't go from one
from one גג gag to another, that you can't even travel within
the גג gag itself because of its, I'm sorry, that's yeah, רב
Rav said you can't move in the גג gag itself. Remember this
debate that if you had, I'll draw it down here, if you
had the two גגות, gagos, which is what the חכמים Chachamim and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon debate, so excuse
me, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים Chachamim where the חכמים
Chachamim say you're not allowed to go from one גג gag to
the next. According to רב, Rav, you can't even go within A,
right, because it's exposed to B, right? So that was רב, Rav,
if you remember that. Within the חכמים Chachamim can you travel on
the roof of A itself? So we taught a ברייתא braisa that
supports רב, Rav, תניא כוותיה דרב, tanya k'vasteh d'Rav, תניא כוותיה דרבי
יהודה, tanya k'vasteh d'Rabbi Yehuda, and we taught a ברייתא braisa that
supports רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda interpretation of what we just said, the
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So
let's take a look. תניא כוותיה דרב, tanya k'vasteh d'Rav, we taught
like רב, Rav, כל גגות העיר רשות אחת הן. kol gagot ha-ir
reshus achas hen. All of the, so this is the position of
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, all of the roofs are one domain. ואסור
להעלות ולהוריד מן הגג לחצר, v'assur l'halos u'le-horid min ha-gag la-chatzer, but
and here's where we see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the
roofs are one but they're distinct from the חצרות. chatzeros. You can't
go from the גג gag to the חצר chatzer מן החצר לגגים
min ha-chatzer la-gagim or from the חצר chatzer to the גג. gag.
וכלים ששבתו בחצר מותר לטלטלן בחצר, v'keilim she-shavsu b'chatzer mutar l'taltelan b'chatzer,
but if it started in the חצר chatzer you can carry it
in the חצר. chatzer. Okay, so this is basically a nice illustration
of what we said that according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the
roofs are their own domain and the חצר's chatzer its own domain.
Okay, בגגים, ba-gagim, and if it started on the roof, מותר לטלטלן.
mutar l'taltelan. And the גג gag you can carry it down the
roofs. Okay. ובלבד שלא יהא גג גבוה עשרה או נמוך מחצר. uvilvad
shelo yehei gag gavoa asarah o namuch mechatzer. As long as you
don't go from a roof you know from one roof to the
next as long as the next roof is not higher or lower
than ten טפחים tefachim away that we discussed in the משנה mishna
and דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So so far it's a
nice just elaboration of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in the משנה, mishna,
but also you know with a nice clarification of the point that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda made a minute ago, which is that all
the גגות gagot are one and all the חצרות chatzerot are one,
but חצר chatzer and גג gag are distinct. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim,
and now here's the חכמים, chachamim, כל אחד ואחד רשות לעצמו. kol
echad ve'echad reshut le'atzmo. Every rooftop is separate, and so you can't
go from roof A to roof B. How about on roof A
itself? ואין מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע. ve'ein metaltelin bo ela be'arba. Even
on one rooftop you can't go more than four אמות, amot, which
is basically how רב Rav explained the חכמים. chachamim. Once you can't
go from A to B and then A is fully exposed to
a place that you can't go to, so you can't even go
more than four אמות amot on A itself. So that ברייתא braita
nicely clarifies that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says each one is distinct
and also nicely clarifies that according to the חכמים, chachamim, the position
of רב Rav that even on one rooftop you cannot go four
אמות. amot. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara says
תניא כוותיה דרבי יהודה, tanya kevasei deRabbi Yehuda, we taught like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in his explanation of the debate of the חכמים
chachamim of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אמר
רבי, amar Rabbi, says רבי, Rabbi, and this is going to prove
that according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon they're all one big unit.
It's not each each is a unit respectively, but גג חצר וקרפף
gag chatzer vekarpef are all the one big unit. אמר רבי כשהיינו
לומדים תורה אצל רבי שמעון בתקוע, amar Rabbi keshehayinu lomdim Torah etzel
Rabbi Shimon biSkoa, when we were learning תורה Torah with רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon in תקוע, Tekoa, היינו מעלין שמן ואלונטית. hayinu ma'alin shemen
ve'aluntit. Now here we would actually bathe on שבת. Shabbos. On שבת
Shabbos according to the גמרא Gemara you are allowed to bathe as
long as it's not in hot water. I mean even water heated
before שבת Shabbos you can't use because you'll come to heat the
water on שבת. Shabbos. But if you have let's say natural hot
springs or something, so it's not even in that whole category of
water that gets heated or you have cold water, you are allowed
to immerse yourself. אשכנזים Ashkenazim do not fully immerse themselves in water
as a later מנהג. minhag. But anyway, so when we were learning
תורה, Torah, it's a funny juxtaposition, when we were learning תורה Torah
here's how we went to the bath on שבת. Shabbos. Okay here's
how we bathed ourselves on שבת. Shabbos. But that's where we were,
we were by his ישיבה yeshiva and on שבת Shabbos we took
our baths and here's what we did.
So כשהיינו לומדים תורה אצל רבי שמעון בתקוע היינו מעלין שמן ואלונטית.
keshehayinu lomdim Torah etzel Rabbi Shimon biSkoa hayinu ma'alin shemen ve'aluntit. We
would take oil because you know a good bath also means like
rubbing yourself with oil and towels, מגג לגג ומגג לחצר ומחצר לחצר
ומחצר לקרפף ומקרפף לקרפף אחר. migag legag umigag lechatzer umichatzer lechatzer umichatzer
lekarpef umikarpef lekarpef acher. Okay, so we would basically go from a
גג gag to a חצר chatzer to a קרפף karpef and we
would do all this type of traveling on שבת Shabbos because they
were all surrounded by walls and finally get to the place where
we would actually take our bath. Okay, עד שהיינו מגיעים אצל המעיין
שהיינו רוחצים בו, ad shehayinu magi'im etzel hama'ayan shehayinu rochtzin bo, until
we got to the well spring that we would bathe ourselves in.
Okay, so therefore anyway it's a nice demonstration that according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, because that's who they were learning תורה Torah by,
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that the גג חצר וקרפף gag chatzer vekarpef
were all one domain and you could as long as you could
and you could go from one to the other. One just one
second, אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
to support this says מעשה בשעת הסכנה, ma'aseh bish'at hasakanah, there was
a story once at a time of danger and והיינו מעלין
ספר תורה מחצר לגג ומגג לחצר ומחצר לקרפף לקרות בו. vehayinu ma'alin
Sefer Torah michatzer legag umigag lechatzer umichatzer lekarpef likrot bo. Maybe they
couldn't have started with the ספר תורה Sefer Torah in the שול
shul beforehand, they were afraid it would get stolen or would make
it too public, so somehow on שבת Shabbos itself they got the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah to where they needed to read from it.
And they would do it by going from גג gag to חצר
chatzer etc. So אמרו לו, amru lo, they said back to him,
אין שעת הסכנה ראיה. ein sha'at hasakanah re'ayah. There is no proof
from a time of danger because maybe they made special allowances there
that they would not otherwise have made. Now it is worth noting
that all of this, going from A to B to C and
whatever, is all has to assume that these things started actually in
the yard, which is a little funny to imagine, to imagine that
right before שבת Shabbos you put your oil and your towels on
the rooftop, maybe the rooftop is the best place because it's secure.
Fine, and then you went from the rooftop to the yard to
the קרפף karpef and so on. But where'd you put your ספר
תורה? Sefer Torah? If you started in a house then you know
you got a problem. So anyway, maybe it was still on the
rooftop, but that's also not clear. It could be why the גמרא
Gemara sort of says that it's that it was שעת הסכנה. sha'at
hasakanah. But you should notice as in the case
about the bathing and the oil and the towels it said that
they started מגג, migag, because to underscore the point again, you can't
take it out
of the house, it has to start in one of the domains,
and the best place for it to start amongst these domains would
be the גג. gag. Did you want to add something רבקה? Rivka?
It's a very different image of שבת Shabbos than the way we
imagine.
Yeah, that they
would start to go to take a bath, and the oil, is
that so clear that you can spread oil?
Yes, so it is funny, you know, there's a whole question about
what are the parameters of ממרח, memareiach, which is this idea of
smoothing something, you know, but as I of course, and what types
of types of things can you rub, or is it ממרח? memareiach?
can you rub in and so on. No, no, no.
Well, do we have this somewhere?
Certain types of oil that are done for the sake of a
חולה, choleh, you know, rose oil I think in and so on,
that was discussed as a רפואה. refuah. But this was a general
thing, like the same way we wash with soap, you know, we
put on a lotion or something. But I do tell people exactly
this, you know, nowadays there's this assumption that a lot of like
smoothing of types of things, I don't know, toothpaste or I don't
know other types of things are ממרח. memareiach. So without getting into
exactly what the parameters are about that, you know, I said look,
certainly if it has the viscosity of oil or less you can
do it, because you know, סיכה sicha was only אסור assur on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It's not אסור assur on שבת, Shabbos, right?
So that would be a regular thing that they would do is
rub oil into their...
Otherwise, what does the prohibition יום כיפור Yom Kippur mean?
Exactly.
And the towels, what are you supposed to?
Well, we had that before, about towels and just you know if,
right, about can you have to be concerned you'll come to squeeze
the towels or not. We had that discussion before. רבי שמעון אומר.
Rabbi Shimon Omer. Okay. So that is a nice clarification of the
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. We're
not done yet. רבי שמעון אומר אחד גגין. Rabbi Shimon Omer echad
gagin. Okay. So אמר רב, Amar Rav, הלכה כרבי שמעון. halacha k'Rabbi
Shimon. So Rav says we rule like Rabbi Shimon, okay? That's the
best, nice, the very... the most lenient position, as long as it
starts in one...
but he still doesn't...
he's even worse than the חכמים. Chachamim. I know. So we have
a lot of debates yesterday about the position of the חכמים, Chachamim,
which is the most restrictive. But להלכה le'halacha we rule like רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. והוא שלא עירבו. Vehu shelo eirvu. Now we get
to the issue I made before. But when is it that you
can take from yard A to yard B and from yard B
to roof C or whatever?
Only if there was no עירוב eiruv in any of these places.
Not only did they not make an עירוב eiruv together, because then
the whole פרק perek is moot, but they didn't even make an
individual עירוב. eiruv. Because, as we're going to see, because if they
made an individual עירוב, eiruv, you're going to have a confusion of
which are the vessels you can move. אבל עירבו לא, Aval eirvu
lo, but if A made an עירוב eiruv in the example I
gave, you cannot take a vessel from A to B. דגזרינן דילמא
אתי לאפוקי מאני דבתים לחצר. Degazrinan dilma ati l'apokei manei de'batim le'chatzer.
We're afraid you'll take a house vessel into the yard. So if
A here, if A here made their own עירוב, eiruv, house vessels
can go out into A's yard. But what you can bring from
yard A to yard B are only yard vessels. And therefore only
something that started in the yard. Well, how are you going to
remember which vessel started in the yard and which one came from
the house? So he says I'm afraid you're not going to remember.
So it's like, you know, it's not a no-cost decision. If you're
going to choose to make your עירוב, eiruv, then you're going to
cut yourself off from B. Unless you don't make an עירוב, eiruv,
then you can go to B. At least the yards are combined.
The houses aren't combined, but the yards are combined. So that decision
of pulling together, you can find a nice sort of sermon in
here somewhere. That decision of sort of making that coherent and pulling
together also separates you, is going to separate you from B. It's
not like you can do both. Unless you make an עירוב eiruv
with B, right. But it's not that you can then go ahead
and do both. Okay, because now הלכתית halachitit you can, but it's
just afraid that they'll come to confuse the two. All right. So
ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar,
and Shmuel says, בין עירבו בין שלא עירבו, bein eirvu bein shelo
eirvu,
whether you made, A made an עירוב eiruv or not, A, they
can bring from the yard vessels from A to B, even though
they can't bring from the house vessels from A to B. But
even if they made an עירוב, eiruv, we're not afraid they'll confuse
it. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן, Vechein amar Rabbi Yochanan,
and so said Rabbi Yochanan. מי לחשך, Mi lachshacha, who whispered to
you to make this distinction? That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it.
בין עירבו בין שלא עירבו, Bein eirvu bein shelo eirvu, doesn't matter
whether they made an עירוב eiruv or not an עירוב. eiruv. Okay,
it's an interesting phrase that תוספות Tosafot points out occurs a number
of times, specifically it's actually interesting, like תוספות Tosafot recognizes that this
is a distinctive tannaitic phrase. If you look at תוספות Tosafot מי
לחשך, mi lachshacha, רש"י לא גריס ליה, Rashi lo garis lei, ואמרי
דאיתא בתורת כהנים בכמה מקומות. ve'amri de'ita be'Torat Kohanim be'khama mekomot. Like
so it's interesting, you don't find it a lot in ש"ס, Shas,
but you find it in the...
איכא דאמרי הכי. Ika de'amri hachi. Yeah.
But you find it in the... so he says you find it
in the ספרא, Sifra, right,
the Torat Kohanim on ויקרא, Vayikra, in a number of places. So
it's anyway, then the way תוספות Tosafot would choose to read it,
he has a couple of interpretations, but one basically is like who
whispered to you to make such a distinction, yes they... whether they
did or didn't make an עירוב. eiruv. You know, all these statements
until now have been categorical. So if you can go from A
to B, it's even if A has an עירוב. eiruv. וכן אמר
רבי... Vechein amar Rabbi...
I'm sorry, I just did it. מתיב ליה רב חסדא לשמואל. Metiv
lei Rav Chisda le'Shmuel. So Rav Chisda said to Shmuel ולרבי יוחנן,
u'le'Rabbi Yochanan, and to Rabbi Yochanan who says, you know, that you
can even with an עירוב eiruv you can go from A to
B. יהיו שני כלים בחצר. Yehyu shnei keilim be'chatzer. What?
I don't understand. What... what's going to be the case? There'll be
two vessels in the yard, בחצר אחת, be'chatzer achat, in one yard.
זה מותר וזה אסור? Ze mutar ve'ze assur? And you're going to
tell me, ah, this one you can bring to the next yard,
that one you can't? So it's just too confusing. You have to
say it's all אסור assur once there's... once there's an עירוב eiruv
in A. So now the גמרא Gemara says, רבי שמעון לטעמיה. Rabbi
Shimon le'taameih. No. So the answer back is, no, Rabbi Shimon actually
goes according to his reasoning. Rabbi Shimon is not concerned that things
will be mixed up. How do you know this? דלא גזר, Dela
gazar, he doesn't make a גזירה. gezeirah. דתנן, Detnan, and now you
might remember this משנה Mishnah from a while ago. אמר רבי שמעון,
Amar Rabbi Shimon, למה הדבר דומה? Lama hadavar domeh? So Rabbi Shimon,
what is this like? Another case, which I'm not going to get
into. לשלוש חצרות הפתוחות זו לזו. Leshallosh chatzerot hapetuchot zu l'zu. You
have three yards were open to one another, ופתוחות לרשות הרבים, ufetuchot
lereshut harabim, and open into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So you
might remember this? We've had this case. I know, yes, we did
have this case.
So this
case was, this is quoting from, now that we're near the end
of the מסכת, masechet, you
know, we'll quote from earlier material rather than before when we were
quoting from later material. So you have these three courtyards, you had
your רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, they were open individually into the רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, so it's not like you had to go from
one to the other to get through, which makes them more considered
on top of another, and theoretically you could get from
one to the next. Now, there was an A-B עירוב eiruv and
there was a B-C עירוב, eiruv, okay? So that's the scenario. Okay,
so שלוש פתוחות זו לזו ופתוחות לרשות הרבים, shalosh petuchot zu lizu
ufetuchot lereshut harabim, ועירבו שתי חיצוניות עם האמצעית, ve'irvu shetei chitzoniyot im
ha'emtza'it, so A made with B and C made with B, היא
מותרת עמהן, hi muteret imahen, B can carry from, you know, you
can carry from B to A and A to B, and you
can get from B to C and
C to B, and הן מותרות עמה, vehen mutarot imah, that's the
other part, ושתי חיצוניות אסורות זו עם זו, ushtei chitzoniyot asurot zu
im zu, but A cannot carry to C. Now, what does that
prove? It says, okay, that's like the obvious point, of course. דילמא
אתי לאפוקי מנא דהאי לחצר דהאי. dilma atei lafukei mana dehai lechatzer
dehai. You go from A to, ah, this is going to be
a problem. What's going to be the problem? If A is going
to carry into B, you're going to have a little A vessel
in B. And if now you're telling me that B is allowed
to carry into C, the B vessel is fine, but in courtyard
B, you'll have B vessels and A vessels, not only that, you'll
also have C vessels right there. So in courtyard B, you're going
to have all different types of vessels, and you have to somehow
keep it straight and remember that which is the B vessel that
can go either way, which is the C vessel that can only
go back to C, and which is the A vessel that can
only go back to A. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is, but
you know what, he's not concerned about it. He thinks you'll keep
it straight and therefore he's not going to allow that concern to
restrict this case. So similarly, it's a very nice comparison. Similarly, even
if you have house vessels here, he's going to not be concerned
and he's still going to let you carry the yard vessels from
A to B. Okay. So that is, yes, I hear your point
that how are you going to keep it straight, but I gotta
tell you, we're talking about רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon does not distinguish. Yes. I guess we could call A,
B, and C milk, פליישיג, fleishig, and פרווה. pareve.
Yeah,
something like that.
My wife said once, I think she said her mother said there's
no such thing as פרווה, pareve, there's only like not yet פליישיג.
fleishig.
All right, anyway, so, so let's take a look.
My son once said, you know, milk and meat makes פרווה. pareve.
Right. Yeah. Yeah, that's the force, the one is טריף. treif. So
anyway, okay, so let's take a look.
Okay. So this is רבי
שמעון.
Rabbi
Shimon. Okay, ולא גזר. velo gazar. So ולא גזר, velo gazar, and
he didn't make a גזרה gezeirah דילמא אתי לאפוקי מנא דהאי חצר
להאי חצר dilma atei lafukei mana dehai chatzer lehai chatzer that you'll
go from A to B and then that same A vessel will
find its way to C. הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too, לא
גזרינן lo gazrinan דילמא אתי לאפוקי מנא דבתים לחצר. dilma atei lafukei
mana debatim lechatzer.
We're not afraid that a house vessel from A will find its
way to B, even if we allow you to take a yard
vessel from A into B. So מתיב רב ששת, metiv Rav Sheshet,
so רב ששת Rav Sheshet asks, רבי שמעון אומר אחד גגות ואחד
חצרות ואחד קרפיפות רשות אחת הן, Rabbi Shimon omer echad gagot ve'echad
chatzeirot ve'echad karpifot reshut achat hen, this is our משנה, mishnah, לכלים
ששבתו בתוכן ולא לכלים ששבתו בתוך הבית. lekeilim sheshavtu betochan velo lekeilim
sheshavtu betoch habayit. That's a straight quote from our משנה mishnah which
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, okay, that, right, גג חצר קרפף, gag
chatzer karpef, and just to make it more fun, we should put
another like גג gag here that you'll take to, I mean actually
take to the גג gag here, whatever, okay, but anyway, okay, so
they're all one רשות reshut for כלים ששבתו בתוך החצר, keilim sheshavtu
betoch hachatzer, which is what we said, a חצר chatzer vessel. So
you can go from A to B and bring the חצר chatzer
vessel and from B to the rooftop, even with no עירוב. eiruv.
That's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה. mishnah. They're all one
רשות. reshut. But now we're going to focus on the last line.
ולא לכלים ששבתו בתוך הבית. velo lekeilim sheshavtu betoch habayit. But if
we're talking about a house vessel, a house vessel there, you cannot
go from A to B and from B to C. Okay, so
the question is, but okay, what's the scenario? If did you make
an עירוב eiruv or not? If you didn't make an עירוב, eiruv,
then you have to tell me you can't take a house vessel
from A to B to C? If you didn't make an עירוב,
eiruv, what can you not do with this house vessel? You can't
even take it to A. So you would have to tell me,
oh, a house vessel, that you can't take from A to B
to C, because obviously you can't even take it out of the
house. So if you have to tell me that you can't go
from A to B to C, obviously we're talking that you did
make an עירוב eiruv and you are taking it out of the
house into the courtyard, and even once you took it out of
the house, don't keep on taking it from B to C. So
that proves that the case we're talking about is with an עירוב,
eiruv, and even so, he allows you to move the yard vessels.
So that's what the גמרא gemara is going to say. בשלמא אי
אמרת דעירבו, bishlama ei amart de'irvu, if you say בשלמא bishlama they
made an עירוב, eiruv, היינו דמשכחת לה מנא דבתים לחצר. hainu demishkachat
lah mana debatim lechatzer. That's how you have a house vessel in
the yard of A and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon has to say
don't take the house vessel from A to B. Now, אי אמרת...
ei amart... but if the whole allowance of א *A* to ב
*B* to ג *C* is when there's no עירוב eruv *eiruv* in
א *A*, so היכי משכחת מאני דביתא בחצר *heichi mishkachat amane de'bayta
bechatzer*, why did he have to say don't take a house vessel
from א *A* to ב *B* to ג *C*? Of course you
can't! You can't even take it into א *A*! So, הוא מותיב
לה והוא מפרק לה *hu mosiv lah vehu mefareik lah*, he asked
it but then he himself suggested the answer. בקומתא וסודרא *bekumpta vesudra*,
we're talking about that you basically have like a scarf and a
hat, which means what? You wore it out of the house. So
what happens is you didn't make an עירוב eruv *eiruv* in א
*A*, no עירוב eruv *eiruv*, you wore your hat out, and then
you took your hat off and you put it on the ground,
okay, and you let it stay there. So now, now you have
to say, now that you got it out there legitimately, you still
cannot bring it into the other part, you know, from א *A*
to ב *B* to ג *C*. Can you put it on your
head and wear it? Yeah, you can pick it up and put
it back on your head and wear it. Okay, anyway, so that's
the scenario. But the simple sense is that we're talking even with
an עירוב eruv *eiruv*, and even with an עירוב eruv. *eiruv* in
א *A*, you're allowed, we're not afraid that you will come to
confuse them. Okay, let's take a look now at צדי א עמוד
ב *Tzadi Aleph amud beis*, תא שמע ta shema. *Tashma*. Okay, עמוד
ב *amud beis* is a lot more fun than yesterday. Yeah, I'm
not saying much. I know, I'm telling you. We have the really
impossible דפים *dapim*, so you appreciate the other ones. תא שמע *Tashma*.
אנשי חצר chatzer ואנשי מרפסת ששכחו ולא עירבו velo eirvu, *anshei chatzer
ve'anshei mirpeset sheshachchu velo eirvu*. There's a little חזרה *chazarah*. You might
remember some of this. The people of the yard and the people
of the balcony that did not make an עירוב eruv. *eiruv* with
one another. Remember that whole section where it was like who has,
who can claim different structures, like to be connected to their yard?
So they did it and they didn't make an עירוב eruv *eiruv*.
כל שגבוה עשרה טפחים למרפסת פחות מכאן לחצר *kol shegavoah asarah tefachim
lemirpeset pachot mikan lachatzer*. Okay, if it's higher than עשרה טפחים *asarah
tefachim* it belongs to the מרפסת *mirpeset*, less than that to the
חצר chatzer *chatzer*. There's a whole debate of exactly how to describe
to explain that, but I'm not going to review all of that,
it's not relevant for us. Let's just look at the simple case.
Here you have your balcony, right, and here you've got your yard,
your חצר chatzer *chatzer*, you have houses below, right, and you've got
houses above, and they did not make an עירוב eruv *eiruv*. So
that's basically a case of א *A* and ב *B*.
They made an עירוב eruv *eiruv*
amongst
themselves, but they did not make an עירוב eruv *eiruv* together. So
you have courtyard א *A* and courtyard ב *B*, and you've got
this, you know, this type of a what do you call, an
עמוד *amud*, this type of a not a post, but a a
pillar that's in the middle here, or a mound. Okay, and the
question is, is this א *A*'s mound or is it ב *B*'s
mound? Who gets to put stuff on the mound? Remember this vaguely
from before? So, if it's high more than עשרה טפחים *asarah tefachim*
it belongs to ב *B*, and they can use it. Less than
עשרה טפחים *asarah tefachim* it belongs to א *A*. Now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said had ways of like re-reading this that means if
it's less than עשרה טפחים *asarah tefachim* it's א *A*'s and ב
*B*'s, but anyway that's not really relevant for us. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does with this. Okay, now, דמאן דאמר שהיו
אלו שרבים ואלו שרבים *dema'an de'amar shehayu elu sherabbim ve'elu sherabbim*. When
is this true? That, you know, that א *A* uses their space
and ב *B* theirs and this mound goes one way or the
other? If א *A* was if there were many people living on
the ground floor and many people living on the balcony and they
all made their and they עירבו *eirvu* and they made their individual
עירובים *Eruvim*. So now א *A* can carry in its own, ב
*B* can carry in its in its own, and the question is
the pillar, does that go to the א *A* zone or the
ב *B* zone? ועירבו אלו לעצמן ואלו לעצמן *ve'eirvu elu le'atzman ve'elu
le'atzman*, each one separately, but they didn't make a joint עירוב eruv?
*eiruv*. או *o*, or another case is, שהיו יחידים *shehayu yechidim*. There's
only one guy living down on א *A* and one guy up
on ב *B*. So they don't need to make an עירוב eruv,
*eiruv* with others and ב *B* has rights to his yard and
א *A* has rights to his yard. And the question is this
mound, whose yard does it go to? שאין צריכים לערב *she'ein tzerichim
le'areiv*, there there's nobody else they have to make an עירוב eruv
*eiruv* with. אבל היו שרבים ושכחו ולא עירבו ve-shachachu velo eirvu *aval
hayu sherabbim veshachchu velo eirvu*. Let's say, however, that there were many
people living in א *A* and many people living in ב *B*
and nobody made any עירוב eruv, *eiruv*. They didn't even make an
עירוב eruv *eiruv* amongst themselves. So your so you're assuming so it's
going to be much worse, right? But the but this presented as
ah, then there's a boon. What's the boon? גג וחצר ואכסדרה ומרפסת
gag ve-chatzer ve-achsadra u-mirpesset כולן רשות אחת הן kulan reshut achat hen.
*gag vechatzer ve'achsaderah umirpeset kulan reshut achat hen*. So then oh, that's
okay, then you can take from anything that started on the מרפסת
*mirpeset* to any חצר chatzer *chatzer* and to any and to any
you know and to any גג gag *gag*. So basically it says
look, this idea of who gets to use this pillar is only
when א *A* made their own עירוב eruv *eiruv* and ב *B*
made their own עירוב eruv. *eiruv*. But if א *A* and ב
*B* did not make their own עירוב eruv, *eiruv*, so it's true
you cannot take out of your house into the חצר chatzer *chatzer*.
But if you've got some vessel that starts in the חצר chatzer
*chatzer*, well, this is a מרפסת *mirpeset*, this is a חצר chatzer,
*chatzer*, this I don't know call this a גג gag *gag* or
whatever you want to call it or part of a חצר chatzer
*chatzer*, so then it doesn't matter whose this belongs to, right? Because
anything that starts in here you can go from here to here
to a חצר chatzer *chatzer* to another חצר chatzer *chatzer* to a
גג gag *gag*, okay.
But so okay that's the position of רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rebbi
Shimon*
that you can go from one to the next. The only question
is why did it say only if they didn't make an עירוב
eruv, *eiruv*? Right? Even if they did make an עירוב eruv *eiruv*
shouldn't that be true about the object that starts out there? So
this is evidence that no, when are we going to let... you
have latitude with the objects that start out in the yard only
when there's no עירוב eruv? so it won't get confused with an
object that started in the house. Is that clear? Meaning this thing
adds by saying oh if you didn't make an עירוב eruv then
you can keep it all within the same domains. Okay, so who
cares even if you did? Clearly if you did make an עירוב
eruv then there's a concern that you will you'll confuse it with
stuff that started in the house. You decide what type of moving
you want to do. You know, it's one type of a permission
versus another. With an עירוב eruv you can take from the houses
out onto the balcony, but you can't take from stuff that's on
the balcony all year. And without the עירוב eruv you can do
the other type of movement, but not... so it's a tradeoff. It's
not one is not just better than the other, it's different than
the other. You decide on the next structure but you don't like
your own structure. Right. But again you have to get this stuff
that you want to move, you gotta get it started out in
the yard before שבת Shabbos begins. Anyway that proves that at least
according to this ברייתא Beraisa there's a leniency the allowance to do
this is only without an עירוב. eruv So the גמרא Gemara says
טעמא ta'ama the reason that we're allowing it is דלא עירבו. delo
eirvu. The last case allowed it because there was no עירוב. eruv,
הא עירבו ha eirvu if there was an עירוב eruv, by A's
by themselves and B's by themselves לא. lo. So you see proves
my point that with an עירוב eruv, it's worse. So the גמרא
Gemara says no הא מני רבנן היא. ha mani rabanan hi. This
isn't רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon this is the רבנן. Rabanan. Do you
remember we positioned we said that there was a רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir position that each one was different, there's a רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon position that they're all the same. We never explained that the
רבנן Rabanan who argue about the roofs and different ownership of the
roofs how would they define the question about similar genres or different
genres? And here we're saying they actually would say a middle position.
ודייקא נמי דלא קתני קרפף ומבוי שמע מינה vedayka nami delo katani
karpaf umavoi shema mina because if you look at the list about
what they said was all one thing in this immediate ברייתא Beraisa
we just quoted that you can go from the balcony to the
חצר chatzer. it says it says גג חצר אכסדרה ומרפסת gag chatzer
achsadra umirpesset but it doesn't say קרפף. karpaf. Now for me and
you קרפף karpaf big deal isn't קרפף karpaf just like the others?
I mean it's just another example. But apparently here's the difference. All
those four גג חצר אכסדרה ומרפסת gag chatzer achsadra umirpesset all those
four are places that are are more frequently used. Meaning think about
the חצר chatzer the yard right in front of your house. It's
not used as much as the house but you know it's it
has a reasonable amount of use. Similarly the rooftop, similarly an אכסדרה
achsadra a portico, the hallway portico you go you use it and
so on. Whereas a קרפף karpaf is more like a type of
a vacant yard if not totally vacant but it's more it has
much less use. And the גמרא Gemara understands that that in principle
is a different type of a category of things. So this ברייתא
Beraisa did not include that in the list. So we until now
have been saying that... right what have we been saying until now?
We've been saying I don't know which one of these to erase
but okay. We've been saying that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. says גג
חצר קרפף gag chatzer karpaf are all one. And רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir says he said כל הגגות kol hagaggot are one which the
גמרא Gemara therefore assumes meant that all the חצרות chatzerot are one
and that all the קרפפות karpafoat are one. And the חכמים Chachamim
who really just argue with him about saying that the גגות gaggot
are distinct so they say the גגות gaggot are separate right גג
א וגג ב. gag aleph vegag bet. But somehow the גמרא Gemara
understands that they would say that if you had not this issue
of different ownership, that's when there's different ownership, but if you did
not have the issue of different ownership somehow they would say that
גג and חצר chatzer. are one and the חצר chatzer קרפף karpaf
is not. Now there's nothing so far that has proven that they
would say that. The גמרא Gemara is going to have some type
of textual evidence in a minute. But that's what they say. This
משנה Mishna about the balcony and the you know and the balcony
and the posts and all of that that said oh if stuff
started outside then you can go from גג to חצר chatzer. to
אכסדרה achsadra etc. But what it did not say was that you
could go to the קרפף. karpaf. So that is not the רבי
שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. That is the חכמים Chachamim not רבי שמעון. Rebbi
Shimon רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is the one that we know from
that case of the three yards right the A B C. He
is the one that is clear that doesn't make גזירות gezeiros that
you're going to come to carry from one to the other because
he was okay with this. So it's within רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
that I'm saying that even if you did not make even if
you did make an עירוב eruv I'm not afraid you'll get confused.
But this ברייתא Beraisa clearly is the חכמים Chachamim because it did
not include קרפף. karpaf. And they don't agree with him. They would
be they would agree that they'd... you'd get confused without an עירוב
eruv, and you'd come to take a house vessel into from you
know to the other yard. Okay so again what this boils down
to is number one the question within רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. that
are we going to allow you to go from A to B
to C even if A has an עירוב? eruv Are we afraid
you'll confuse it with then with a house vessel? And the argument
is that we are not afraid of that. Okay then what we
introduced is that the חכמים Chachamim actually are a middle position between
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and the רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon And they
say everything is one domain of things that are normally used. קרפף
Karfof is its own type of a domain. And now that we
had this problem of this ברייתא, baraita, we said fine. That's not
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position, that's the חכמים. Chachamim. And other positions
would say that when you make an עירוב, eruv it's worse because
then we're afraid you'll be confused. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
not saying that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה
shma mina that is a good proof that this is not a
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon ברייתא. baraita. תא שמע. Let's try to get
prove it again, this question of whether the עירוב eruv, makes it
worse in one way or the other. חמש חצרות הפתוחות זו לזו,
Chamesh chatzerot hapetuchot zo lezo, three wasn't enough, you have five yards
open one to the other ופתוחות למבוי u-petuchot le-mavoi and they all
open up into an alley. Okay. ושכחו כולם ולא עירבו veshachachu kulam
velo eirvu and they all forgot and didn't make an עירוב, eruv,
meaning they didn't even make an עירוב eruv amongst themselves. You have
A, B, C, and D, and nobody made an עירוב eruv, even
amongst themselves. ולא עירבו, velo eirvu. אסור להכניס ולהוציא מחצר למבוי ומן
המבוי לחצר, assur lehachnis ulehotzi mechatzer lemavoi umin hamavoi lechatzer, then you
cannot take from the חצר chatzer to the מבוי mavoi or the
מבוי mavoi to the חצר, chatzer אבל כלים ששבתו בחצר מותר לטלטלם
בחצר aval kelim she-shavtu be-chatzer mutar letaltelam be-chatzer ובמבוי אסור. u-ve-mavoi assur.
So here let me just hold on one second, let me just
double check רש״י Rashi for a second. Right. So, right, okay, so
this basically says you have the... so this is the position that
says you cannot go from the חצר chatzer to the מבוי. mavoi.
Why can you not go from the חצר chatzer to the מבוי?
mavoi? Because this is a... we're assuming that this is exactly the
חכמים Chachamim who say that a קרפף Karfof is set off by
itself and that together with a קרפף Karfof goes a מבוי, mavoi,
an alleyway. Okay. So basically you have the case that you've got
these five חצרות, chatzerot, we'll make it three, it doesn't really matter,
A, B, and C, and here is your מבוי mavoi that they
open up into. Okay, and it says they all forgot and did
not make an עירוב. eruv So what does it say the הלכה
halacha is? Let's read that again. ולא עירבו. ושכחו כולם ולא עירבו
אסור להכניס ולהוציא מחצר למבוי ומן המבוי לחצר. veshachachu kulam velo eirvu
assur lehachnis ulehotzi mechatzer lemavoi umin hamavoi lechatzer. You cannot go from
an A place thing, you cannot bring into the מבוי. mavoi. Why
can you not bring it into the מבוי? mavoi? Because that's going
from one genre to the next. This is assumed to be the
חכמים. Chachamim. So חצר chatzer and מבוי mavoi are a distinct genre
and therefore you cannot do it. אסור להכניס ולהוציא מחצר למבוי ומן
המבוי לחצר. assur lehachnis ulehotzi mechatzer lemavoi umin hamavoi lechatzer. Now hold
on a second. Why is that just חכמים? Chachamim? Maybe it could
be everybody? Because the גמרא's Gemara assuming that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon.
said it's all the same. But he didn't talk... alright, well we'll
see in a minute. No because before you had the case of
a קרפף Karfof and the גמרא Gemara assumed right by the case
about the towels and the oil and the גמרא Gemara assumes that
קרפף Karfof and מבוי mavoi are the same. I don't know because
there's no basis to assume it's different. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara...
assumed that based on their use that was the logical grouping. ושכחו
כולם ולא עירבו אסור להכניס ולהוציא מחצר למבוי ומן המבוי לחצר וכלים
ששבתו בחצר מותר לטלטלם בחצר ובמבוי אסור. veshachachu kulam velo eirvu assur
lehachnis ulehotzi mechatzer lemavoi umin hamavoi lechatzer ve-kelim she-shavtu be-chatzer mutar letaltelam
be-chatzer u-ve-mavoi assur. But if you have your A vessel, you can't
go to the מבוי, mavoi, but you can take your A vessel
anywhere in the חצר. chatzer You can take even without an עירוב,
eruv you can take the courtyard vessels within the חצר chatzer itself.
Okay fine. So basically what do we see though from that ברייתא?
baraita? We see that it is the position of the חכמים Chachamim
and assumes that a מבוי mavoi is distinct from the חצרות. chatzerot.
Okay. Now we're not done. ובמבוי אסור. u-ve-mavoi assur. Now interestingly though
a vessel that starts in a מבוי mavoi is worse than a
vessel that starts in a חצר. A vessel that starts in a
חצר even without an עירוב, eruv you can take it within the
חצר. But if it starts in a מבוי, mavoi, you can't take
it, you know, you can't take it in the מבוי mavoi itself.
Why that should be different we will see in a minute. רבי
שמעון מתיר. Rabbi Shimon mattir. Now our focus is to get to
the רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows going from
the חצר to the מבוי. mavoi. שהיה רבי שמעון אומר, shehaya Rabbi
Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon used to say כל זמן שהן
של רבים kol zman she-hen shel rabbim as long as the courtyards
are many people ושכחו ולא עירבו and nobody made an עירוב eruv
גג וחצר ואכסדרה ומרפסת and then it adds וקרפף ומבוי. ve-karfof u-mavoi.
So all the different things including not only the גג and חצר
whatever but including the קרפף Karfof and the מבוי mavoi even those
things that are used even less כולן רשות אחת הן. They're all
one domain. Okay, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says not a problem
if you had something in A you are allowed to bring it
into the מבוי. mavoi. These are all... according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that would actually be okay. Right that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon
position. Okay but now the גמרא's Gemara gonna say okay I get
that but why did he say as long as you have many
people living and they didn't make an עירוב? eruv Okay even if
they did make an עירוב eruv it sounds like he's restricting it.
If they didn't make an עירוב eruv so we're not gonna get
house vessels there then you can go from the yard to the
מבוי. mavoi. Okay that's the way the גמרא... Gemara but presumably if
they did make an עירוב eruv within A you... טעמא דלא עירבו,
taama d'lo eirvu, the reason he allows you to take a yard
vessel from A to B or from whatever, from A to the
מבוי, mavoi, is because there's no עירוב eruv in A. הא עירבו,
ha eirvu, if they made an עירוב eruv, in A, לא, lo,
he wouldn't allow it. So the גמרא Gemara says no. מאי לא
עירבו? mai lo eirvu? When it says if they didn't make an
עירוב, means לא עירבו חצרות בהדי הדדי. lo eirvu chatzeros bahadi hadadi.
החצר ובתים עירבו. hachatzer uvatim eirvu. So it says no, all he
meant to say is if A, B, and C did not make
a big עירוב, then even so—it's not saying only in that case—even
in that case that they didn't make a big עירוב, it doesn't
matter. If you've got a yard vessel, you can still go from
A to B to C and into the מבוי, mavoi, etc. So
when he said לא עירבו, lo eirvu, it wasn't "I'm going to
allow it because there's no עירוב in it." What he's saying is
it's going to—when it's necessary because there's no ABC עירוב, then in
that type of a case, you can still carry as long as
the vessel started in the yard, you can still go from one
domain to the next. Okay, so he's not limiting it to the
case of no עירוב in A. What he's saying is that when
there's no ABC עירוב and we have to talk about this case,
then I'll tell you it will still be allowed as long as
it began as a yard vessel and you're moving it between this
whole category. So the גמרא Gemara. says, והא לא עירבו קתני, veha
lo eirvu katani, you can't do that. It says they didn't make
an עירוב, which seems to be that nobody made an עירוב, and
they didn't make an עירוב in A either. No, no. מאי לא
עירבו? mai lo eirvu? לא נשתתפו. lo nishtatfu. No, that's not true.
לא עירבו lo eirvu means they did not make the big עירוב,
the שיתוף, shituf, which would have then included the מבוי mavoi as
well. Okay, but bottom line is it just means that there's no
big עירוב that encompasses them all, and therefore you need my ruling.
And in that case, I will rule for you that as long
as it started in the yard, you're okay to bring it to
other similar spaces. ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'is eima, and if you want, I'll
tell you, רבי שמעון לדבריהם דרבנן קאמר. Rabbi Shimon l'divreihem d'Rabbanan ka'amar.
Rabbi Shimon, you're right, he's talking in a scenario that there was
no עירוב within A. Okay, but why does he point that out?
Not because he needs that, but to make an argument to those
that oppose him. And he's saying like the following, you know, לדידי,
l'didi, as far as I'm concerned, Rabbi Shimon would say, לא שנא
עירבו ולא שנא לא עירבו. lo shena eirvu v'lo shena lo eirvu.
I wouldn't care if there was an עירוב in A or not
an עירוב in A. I think I'm not afraid of things being
confused, and I think that you can go from A to B
to C as long as you don't use a house vessel. אלא
לדידכו, ella l'didchu, I would get that you would have a problem
if there was an עירוב in A, because then it will lead
to confusions of which is a house vessel, which is a yard
vessel. אבל אודו לי מיהת, aval odu li mi'as, at least you
should concede, דהיכא דלא עירבו, d'heicha d'lo eirvu, if there's no עירוב
in A and there's no confusion of house vessels or yard vessels,
so at least in that case you should concede to me that
רשות אחת היא, reshus achas hi, you can go from the yard
to the מבוי. mavoi. ואמרו ליה רבנן, v'amru lei Rabbanan, and the
Rabbis say back, לא, שאר רשויות במבוי אסורין. lo, shear reshuyos bamavoi
asurin. No, sorry, even if we're not afraid of confusion, we think
a מבוי mavoi is a different genre than the house. Okay, so
again, we are not introducing a lot of ideas here. Okay, the
one question about what are considered your different domains: רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, each one is distinct; okay, the חכמים, Chachamim, when there's not
an issue of different ownership, has גג חצר אכסדרה, gag chatzer achsadra,
like the things that are generally used here, קרפף kufar and מבוי
mavoi are different; and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, has them all together.
And when you start in one, you can move within the same
sort of circle of things. Okay, and then the question we've been
focusing on is, with a separate issue, would this be even if
there was an עירוב and you might get confused whether it's a
house vessel and a yard vessel? And we're saying that—and we're arguing
that according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon he's not afraid of that
confusion. This recent ברייתא braisa that seemed to be concerned about that
confusion was only רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, conceding a point to those
that argue with him, but actually from his perspective, it really would
not matter. That's at least the argument. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: לימא מסייע ליה—I'm leima mesayei lei sorry—ובמבוי אסור.
uvamavoi asur. הא אמר מר, ha amar mar, ובמבוי אסור. uvamavoi asur.
So now we're going to get to the last part of that
ברייתא braisa that said that something that started—if it starts in the
yard, then everybody agrees you can carry it within the yard itself,
right? So if something here starts in the yard, of course you
can carry it within the yard itself, according to everybody. But what
about if it starts in the מבוי, mavoi, a vessel that begins
its life, we'll call it a men, in the מבוי? mavoi? Can
you move it within the מבוי? mavoi? So the ברייתא braisa seems
to say no, within the מבוי mavoi it's forbidden, and it didn't
explain why it's different. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara Okay. לימא מסייע ליה leima mesayei lei לרבי זירא? l'Rabbi Zeira?
This seems to support רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. דאמר רב—דאמר רבי זירא
אמר רב, מבוי שלא נשתתפו בו, mavoi shelo nishtatfu bo, if you
didn't make a שיתוף shituf for the מבוי, mavoi, אין מטלטלין אלא
בארבע אמות, ein m'talt'lin ella b'arba amos, then you can only carry
four אמות. amos. Maybe he considers this is—doesn't matter according to who,
because this is not going from A to B—oh, yeah, you're right,
this is—I'm sorry, I take that back—this is according to the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Okay, so he says anyway if it starts in the מבוי,
mavoi, you can only, you only have four אמות. amot. Okay, if
it actually starts in the yard, it gives you more latitude, but
starts in the מבוי, mavoi, you only have four אמות. amot. So
the גמרא Gemara says and it’s not exactly clear why that’s different,
but maybe it’s because a מבוי mavoi as a street is a
little bit more כרמלית-like. carmelit And therefore maybe he wanted to give
it like the status of a כרמלית, carmelit, it seems to be
a reasonable explanation. There’s other גמרות Gemaras that explain it otherwise based
on similar concerns here about would you get it confused with which
types of vessels you’re dealing with. But anyway, so anyway, that seems
to support the idea that מבוי mavoi is different. So the גמרא
Gemara says אימא ולמבוי אסור. eima u-lemavoi assur. When it says that
the מבוי mavoi is forbidden, it does not mean you can’t carry
מבוי mavoi vessels in it. It means you cannot carry it into
the מבוי mavoi from a yard. ולמבוי, u-lemavoi, not to the מבוי
mavoi is אסור. assur. Not within the מבוי, mavoi, but to the
מבוי. mavoi. So the גמרא Gemara says even if it started in
the yard of a חצר because it's the חכמים Chachamim that see
yards and מבואות mavoies as different things. So the גמרא Gemara says
why didn't the מבוי mavoi make a שיתוף, shituf, you know? Okay,
fine, but they didn't, they forgot. So the גמרא says היינו רישא,
hainu reisha, but that's what we said at the beginning. We said
that according to the חכמים Chachamim as opposed to רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon you can't go from the yard to a מבוי. mavoi. So
why would you say it again? משנה יתירה איצטריכי, Mishni yeseira itztrechei,
it's telling it a second time to like tell you a new
point. מהו דתימא כי פליגי רבנן אדרבי שמעון הני מילי היכא דעירבו
ma d'teima ki pligi Rabbanan a-de-Rabbi Shimon hani mili heicha de-irvu going
back to our theme from before. Maybe when the rabbis say that
you can't go from the חצר to the מבוי, mavoi, that's because
you made an עירוב in it and therefore again the concern about
house vessels. אבל היכא דלא עירבו מודו ליה, aval heicha delo irvu
modlei, maybe they would agree that if there was no עירוב and
there was no issue of confusion, you can go from a חצר
to a מבוי. mavoi. קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, so it reiterated
in the חכמים, Chachamim, we really mean it. You can never go
from a חצר to a מבוי. mavoi. Okay, so the חכמים Chachamim
are saying you can't go from a חצר to a מבוי mavoi
whether yes or no עירוב, it's not about that. It's about different
domains and that's this middle position that says not everything is distinct
but not everything is the same. מבוי mavoi and קרפף karpaf are
distinct from the rest. And רבי שמעון that says that they're all
the same. Can if something starts in a מבוי mavoi can you
carry it in a מבוי mavoi without a שיתוף? shituf? That we
have not clarified. Why would a מבוי mavoi be different? Not exactly
clear. Maybe a concern of other vessels that would be there, which
another גמרא says, maybe because a מבוי mavoi has slightly more, you
know, street and therefore כרמלית carmelit qualities to it. But anyway, that
we have not yet resolved. Okay, and that's it for today. We'll
see you all on Shabbos. Q-shul time? Look at that, we finished
eight minutes early. Today's דף daf was really relatively easy.